Finding Aid for the Edwin Bower Hesser Papers LSC.1071
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Negatives, ca. 1920-1946; 13.5 boxes, 0.5 oversize box
  - B. Anonymous subjects, ca. 1920-1946
    - Modeling couples--assorted, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of assorted unidentified modeling couples.
    - Modeling couples--swimming pool, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Various sizes. Black and white portraits and head shots s of couple at swimming pool.
    - Modeling couples--women, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of 2 women posing together in formal and casual attire.
    - Men--casual attire, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified men in casual attire. Includes test print.
    - Men--cowboy and western attire, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified men in cowboy and western attire.
    - Men--formal attire, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified men in formal attire (coat and tie).
    - Men--gardening, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified man gardening outdoors.
    - Men--military uniforms, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      4 x 5 black and white and color portraits and head shots of unidentified men in military uniforms. Includes test prints.
    - Men--shirtless, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified men posing shirtless.
    - Miscellaneous subjects (1 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      Various sizes. Black and white shots of miscellaneous subjects such as animals, architecture, landscapes, and nature.
    - Miscellaneous subjects (2 of 3), ca. 1920-1945 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      4 x 5" black and white shots of miscellaneous subjects such as animals, architecture, landscape, nature, and horse race.
    - Miscellaneous subjects (3 of 3), ca. 1920-1945 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Military procession, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      4 x 5" black and white action shots of an unidentified military procession or parade. Includes shots of unidentified man in military uniform and military vehicles.
    - Theatrical production, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      4 x 5" black and white action shots of an unidentified theatrical production. Includes shots of women posing in various lavish, 18th century themed costumes.
    - Wedding, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 15)
      4 x 5" black and white action shots of an unidentified wedding ceremony. Includes shots of reception, wife and husband posing, and ceremony.
    - Women--bathing suits and beach scenes modeling (1 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait and action shots of unidentified women modeling bathing suits or beach-related attire. Includes shots taken at the beach.
    - Women--bathing suits and beach scenes modeling (2 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Women--bathing suits and beach scenes modeling (2 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Women--bed and couch scenes modeling, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified women posing while laying on a bed or couch.
    - Women--casual attire (1 of 6), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of unidentified women in casual attire, such as sweaters, blouses, and dresses.
    - Women--casual attire (2 of 6), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Women--casual attire (3 of 6), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Women--casual attire (4 of 6), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Women--casual attire (5 of 6), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Women--casual attire (6 of 6), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Women--dance modeling, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white action shots of unidentified women dancing.
    - Women--exterior modeling (1 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of women modeling outdoors. Framed in medium and long shots.
    - Women--exterior modeling (2 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (1 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling ruffled, low cut, and strapless attire. Includes shots of women in Latin-inspired dress and women in various costumes.
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (2 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (3 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      5 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling ruffled, low cut, and strapless attire. Includes shots of women in Latin-inspired dress and women in various costumes.
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (4 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      6 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling ruffled, low cut, and strapless attire. Includes shots of women in Latin-inspired dress and women in various costumes.
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (5 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      7 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling ruffled, low cut, and strapless attire. Includes shots of women in Latin-inspired dress and women in various costumes.
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (6 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      8 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling ruffled, low cut, and strapless attire. Includes shots of women in Latin-inspired dress and women in various costumes.
    - Women--festive, international, ruffled, and costume attire modeling (7 of 7), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      9 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling ruffled, low cut, and strapless attire. Includes shots of women in Latin-inspired dress and women in various costumes.
    - Women--formal attire (1 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women in formal attire, such as furs and gowns.
    - Women--formal attire (2 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Women--formal attire (3 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Women--hats, veils, and headwear modeling (1 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Various sizes. Black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling hats, veils, or other types of headwear. Includes black and white shots of veiled woman wearing mask.
    - Women--hats, veils, and headwear modeling (2 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women modeling hats, veils, or other types of headwear.
    - Woman--interior modeling (1 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of women modeling various clothes indoors. All shots framed in medium and long or long shots.
    - Woman--interior modeling (2 of 2), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Women--props modeling, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of women modeling with various props. Includes shots of women modeling with flowers, fruit, household appliances, gun, swing, soda bottle, sausages, magazine cover, and western wear and props.
    - Women--semi-formal and business attire (1 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women in semi-formal and business attire, such as blouses, dresses, and suits.
    - Women--semi-formal and business attire (2 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      5 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women in semi-formal and business attire, such as blouses, dresses, and suits.
    - Women--semi-formal and business attire (3 of 3), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      6 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women in semi-formal and business attire, such as blouses, dresses, and suits.
    - Women--semi-nude, nude, and erotic attire modeling (1 of 4), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      6.5 x 8" black and white portrait shots of women modeling semi-nude, nude, and in lingerie, erotic, and revealing attire. Includes exterior shots and shots of women laying down and covered by bed sheet or transparent drape.
    - Women--semi-nude, nude, and erotic attire modeling (2 of 4), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Women--semi-nude, nude, and erotic attire modeling (3 of 4), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Women--semi-nude, nude, and erotic attire modeling (4 of 4), ca. 1943-1945 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Women--western attire, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      4 x 5" black and white portraits and head shots of women in country-western attire. Includes shots of women posing with cowboy hats and plaid shirts.
    - Women--winter and Christmas attire modeling, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of women modeling winter and Christmas themed attire, such as ski suits, skis, hooded coats, etc.
    - Women--with children, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      6.5 x 8.25" and 4 x 5" black and white portrait shots of unidentified women posing with children.
    - Oversized negatives, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 40, Folder 3)
      Various sizes of large format negatives consisting of portraits and modeling. Negatives are left loose and in original envelopes in box.
    - Women--head shots, undated (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Oversize--Woman--various, undated (Box 57, Folder 13)
- Assorted paper materials, 1917-1958; 6.5 boxes, 4.5 oversize boxes
  This series consists of paper materials related to the work of Edwin Bower Hesser. Arranged in subseries A-C as follows:
  A. Miscellaneous, 1917-1958
  B. Periodicals, 1920-1958
  C. Posing ideas, ca. 1925-1958.
  - A. Miscellaneous, 1917-1918
    This subseries consists of miscellaneous paper materials related to the work of Edwin Bower Hesser. Items include: assorted letters, invention ideas, Hessercolor patents and documentation, model release forms, and experiment workbooks. Files are arranged alphabetically according to folder title.
    - Agfa Ansco 100 year anniversary publication, 1942; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Publication documenting the development of photography and the Agfa Ansco corporation.
    - Assorted letters, 1931-1954; 14 items. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Letters and telegraphs regarding publishing of photographs, personal matters, and business arrangements and agreements.
    - Car accident report, 1948 August; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Hesser's typed account of a traffic accident.
    - Coronet Magazine correspondence, 1946 March-April; 6 items. (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Correspondence between Hesser and Coronet Magazine regarding publication of color photos.
    - Cunningham Mines company folder, 1928-1929; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Bound company folder containing minutes, by-laws, directors, and shareholders from Consolidated Queen Beens Mines, Ltd for which Clarence Cunningham was president.
    - Cunningham Mines material (1 of 2), 1924-1940; 2 items. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Includes bound official share certificates and bound plan of capital structure readjustment.
    - Cunningham Mines material (2 of 2), 1942-1943; 12 items. (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Includes bound reports and data concerning International Metals, Inc, mine maps, and letters to Hesser regarding business of the mines.
    - Divorce, biography, and court materials, 1921-1956; ca. 25 items. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      Includes legal materials, correspondence, and autobiographies regarding Hesser's divorce and legal matters with ex-wife, Rhea May Reed. Also includes chronologies of events related to ex-wife and health.
    - Fireman's Fund insurance contract, 1951 October 23; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 9)
      Eve Hesser's insurance contract pertaining to list of photographic equipment.
    - Flock insulation for military aircraft materials, 1942, 1944; ca. 50 items. (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Contains correspondence with Claremont Waste Manufacturing Co. and Hesser as well as notes, summaries, and patent applications for development of interior insulation for military aircraft.
    - For the Freedom of the World publicity newspaper, ca. 1917; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Exhibitors' press sheet of film For the Freedom of the World written by Hesser and presented by Ira M. Lowry. Press sheet is in the form of a war time newspaper. Includes image of Barbara Castleton.
    - Forest Lawn Cemetery pictorial, 1944; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 2)
      Bound picture book of Forest Lawn attractions.
    - Hessercolor correspondence, 1930-1940; ca. 30 items. (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Assorted correspondence related to Hesser's color photography and printing business.
    - Hessercolor contracts, patents, and legal documents., 1936-1939; 13 items. (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Assorted documents related to color photography and printing.
    - Hessercolor patent applications, 1937-1941; 2 items. (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Bound applications for letters patent related to color photography and printing.
    - Hessercolor publicity materials, ca. 1937; 2 items. (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Hessercolor advertising brochure and sales sheet.
    - List of subjects in Hessercolor negative sets, 1934; 2 items. (Box 14, Folder 7)
      List of names and number of shots of people in photographs.
    - Military inventions (1 of 2), 1941-1945; ca. 45 items. (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Summaries, calculations, and pitches of various military-related inventions developed during World War II. Inventions include: bomb sighting methods, aerial trajectory, various photographic innovations, and camouflage. Includes handwritten charts and graphs.
    - Military inventions (2 of 2), 1941-1945; 7 items. (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Summaries, calculations, and pitches of various military-related inventions developed during World War II. Inventions include: bomb sighting methods, aerial trajectory, and various photographic innovations. Includes handwritten charts, graphs, and calculations.
    - Military invention patent materials, 1941-1944; 8 items. (Box 14, Folder 10)
      Patent application materials related to various inventions.
    - Men Over Forty, by Albert Cowles and Harry Clorck and unknown story, ca. 1943-1940; 2 items. (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Bound type-written short story and unknown hand written story.
    - Photographic printer sketches and photographic print, ca. 1935; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Technical drawings and black and white print of L.C. Machinery Co. Inc. photo printer.
    - Photographic products advertising brochures, ca. 1938-1942; 3 items. (Box 14, Folder 13)
      DuPont cellophane and Waterlox products brochures.
    - Photography logbooks, ca. 1935-1942; 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Bound logbooks containing information regarding photo shoots, exposures, and developers.
    - Publicity contract, 1931 May 17; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Formal agreement between Hesser and Ben Rowan regarding Hesser's promotion and publicizing of Rowan as an actor.
    - Real estate materials, 1939-1951; 7 items. (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Blueprint, certificates of redemption, and correspondence regarding Hesser's Los Angeles real estate.
    - Season's greeting cards and business cards, ca. 1935-1942; 16 items. (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Black and white print of nude woman posing outdoors used for Hesser's holiday card. Also includes his business cards.
    - Taxes materials, 1945-1958; ca. 20 items. (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Includes receipts, costs, expenditure lists, and letters concerning tax payments.
    - Workbook, 1943-1944; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Bound workbook containing dated notes, scientific tables, calculations, and graphs concerning experiments and developments (for oversize materials see box 38, folders 1 thru 4).
    - Model release forms (1 of 3), ca. 1930-1950; ca. 150 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Signed forms by models giving Hesser right to publish photographs.
    - Model release forms (2 of 3), ca. 1930-1950; ca. 150 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Model release forms (3 of 3), ca. 1930-1950; ca. 90 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Model directory, 1949; 1 item. (Box 37, Folder 1)
      Eve Hesser's model directory. Contains handwritten names, phone numbers, and addresses of models. Cover of directory indicates Eve Hesser and year.
    - Oversize miscellaneous scrapbook, ca. 1938; 1 item. (Box 37, Folder 2)
      Bound scrapbook containing loose items such as chemical solution instructions, photo processing instructions, letters, and notes.
    - Oversize experiments workbook (1 of 6), ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 38, Folder 1)
      Bound workbook containing notes on various photo experiments. Signed by Eve Hesser.
    - Oversize experiments workbook (2 of 6), ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Oversize experiments workbook (3 of 6), ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 38, Folder 3)
      Bound workbook containing notes on various photo experiments.
    - Oversize experiments workbook (4 of 6), ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Oversize experiments workbook (5 of 6), ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Oversize experiments workbook (6 of 6), ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - B. Periodicals, 1920-1958
    This subseries consists of periodical publicaions of Edwin Bower Hesser's photography and articles concerning the Hessercolor process. Items include: Hesser's own publication Arts Monthly Pictorial, shots of numerous Hollywood personalities on magazine covers, assorted published Hessercolor work, and nude, semi-nude, and erotic publications which include work by Hesser. Files are arranged alphabetically by name of publication.
    - American Cinematographer, 1937 July; 2 items. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      No cover; includes article on Hessercolor.
    - American Girl, 1946 January-August; 8 items. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Vol. 29, No. 1, No. 2, No. 4, No. 6, and No. 8; cover photos by Hesser. Covers only for April and June issues (No. 4 and No. 6).
    - Art Photography, 1952 June; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Vol. 3, No. 12; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Artists' Notebook, 1930-1931; 2 items. (Box 20, Folder 4)
      No. 6 and No. 8; magazines are comprised of modeling nude women. Photographers not credited.
    - Arts Monthly Pictorial (1 of 3), 1925 May-August; 7 items. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Vol. 2, No. 4, No. 5, and Vol. 3, No. 1; Hesser is credited as founder, editor, publisher, and photographer (for oversize materials see box 39, folder 1).
    - Arts Monthly Pictorial (2 of 3), 1926 August, December; 3 items. (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Vol. 4, No. 5 and No. 9; Hesser is credited as founder, editor, and photographer. Includes March issue from unknown year and an unknown publication with similar Hesser content (for oversize materials see box 39, folder 1).
    - Consumer Reports, 1966 November; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Vol. 31, No. 11; Christmas Buying Issue.
    - Cover Girls Models, 1950 June, August; 2 items. (Box 20, Folder 8)
      Vol. 1, No. 4, and No. 6; article photos by Hesser.
    - Dammernas Varld, 1947; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 9)
      No. 1; Swedish magazine cover photo by Hesser.
    - Everywoman's Magazine, 1946 March, July; 5 items. (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Vol. 7, No. 3, and No. 7; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Family Circle, 1946 April, September; 7 items. (Box 20, Folder 11)
      Vol. 28, No. 16 and September issue; cover and article photos by Hesser. September issue does not have cover.
    - French Models, 1931; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 12)
      No. 5; magazine is comprised of modeling nude women. Photographers are not credited.
    - Hela Varlden, ca. 1946; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 13)
      Vol. 20, No. 52; Swedish magazine cover photo by Hesser.
    - Hollywood Magazine (1 of 2), 1935-1936; 7 items. (Box 20, Folder 14)
      Covers and title pages from Vol. 25, No. 3, No. 6, and No. 10; includes May, July, October, and December covers from unknown year and volume. Cover and article photos by Hesser. Subjects of covers include: Jeanette MacDonald, Shirley Temple, Ginger Rogers.
    - International Photographer, 1934 January; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Milady, 1944-1945; 8 items. (Box 20, Folder 16)
      Vol. 3, No. 12, and Vol. 4, No. 3, No. 5, No. 8, and No. 9; cover and article shots by Hesser.
    - Minicam Photography, 1947 February; 2 items. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Cover and title pages from Vol. 10, No. 5; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Modern Romances, 1948 January; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Cover and title pages Vol. 35, No. 2; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Movie Classic, 1935-1936; 3 items. (Box 21, Folder 3)
      Vol. 8, No. 5 and cover and title page from Vol. 11, No. 2; includes August cover from unknown year and volume. Cover photos by Hesser.
    - Movies, 1944 September; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Vol. 8, No. 2; article photos by Hesser.
    - People and Places, 1950 March; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Cover of unknown volume; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Perfect Love, ca. 1945 April-May; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 6)
      No. 4; comic book with cover photo by Hesser.
    - Personal Romances, 1946-1947; 6 items. (Box 21, Folder 7)
      Vol. 12, No. 11, Vol. 13, No. 4, No. 5, and No. 9; cover and article photos by Hesser.
    - Pictorial California, ca. 1937; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Souvenir photo book of Southern California landmarks.
    - Popular Photography, 1945-1950 January; 9 items. (Box 21, Folder 9)
      Covers and title pages from Vol. 17, No. 6, Vol. 25, No. 5, and Vol. 26, No. 1; also includes December cover from unknown volume. Cover photos by Hesser.
    - Rangefinder, 1958 August; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 10)
      Vol. 7, No. 8; photography trade publication.
    - Real Romances, 1946 October; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 11)
      Vol. 4, No. 9; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Real Story, 1946-1947; 5 items. (Box 21, Folder 12)
      Vol. 5, No. 6 and Vol. 6, No. 8; cover photos by Hesser.
    - Revealing Romances, 1950-1951; 5 items. (Box 21, Folder 13)
      Covers and title pages from No. 12; also includes October-November cover from unknown volume and number. Cover photos by Hesser.
    - Romantic Marriage, ca. 1946 April; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 14)
      Cover and title pages from April issue, No. 12, unknown year; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Romantic Range, 1946-1947; 5 items. (Box 21, Folder 15)
      Covers and title pages from Vol. 22, No. 2 and Vol. 23, No. 3; cover photos by Hesser.
    - Screen Play, 1936-1937; 6 items. (Box 21, Folder 16)
      Covers and title pages from Vol. 20, No. 138, No. 140, No. 142, No. 144, No. 145; also includes October cover from unknown year, volume, and number. Cover photos by Hesser.
    - Secrets, 1950 July; 6 items. (Box 21, Folder 17)
      Cover and title pages from Vol. 28, No. 2; cover photo by Hesser.
    - Silver Screen, ca. 1944; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 18)
      Cover from June issue, unknown year, volume, and number. Cover is of a painted photo of Jean Harlow.
    - Studio Art Studies (1 of 2), 1930-1931; 3 items. (Box 21, Folder 19)
      No. 10, No. 14, No. 16; magazines are comprised of modeling nude women. Photos by Hesser and Dwight Russell (for oversize materials see box 39, folder 11).
    - Studio Light, 1936 April; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 20)
      Vol. 27, No. 1; Eastman Kodak Company photography-trade publication.